# 陕西·西安
Xi'an, Shaanxi
# 今天中午 决定去吃米皮
We decide to eat Mipi (lit:rice skin) this noon
# 拿一个大份的 再要一个冰峰
A large mipi and a bingfeng (soft drink)
# 一个大碗米皮 一个冰峰汽水
A large bowl of mipi and a bingfeng
# 对
yeah
# 11块钱（9+2）
11 yuan
# 几碗 你要的是
How many bowls?
# 一碗
A bowl
# 先喝点吧
Let’s drink first
# 我看着大哥加了好多醋
I saw the bro added a lot of vinegar into mipi
# 看看是不是
Let’s take a look
# 它这个是米皮加了佐料之后
The mipi is like, after adding the seasonings
# 用最后的几根米皮 蘸了辣子 放在上面
The last few strips are dipped in chili and put on the top
# 相对于面来说 米皮是更加光滑的
Compared to noodle, mipi is smoother
# 而且是这种爽口 弹口的
And more crunchy and al dente
# 这个是要的大份的 除了米皮之外 还加了豆芽
I ordered a large size with extra bean sprouts
# 看着是红油油的 但是吃起来是香而不辣
It looks red and oily, and it tastes fragment but not spicy
# 它是调好味道的 就是吃起来稍微咸点 既当菜又当饭
It's pre-seasoned, which tastes a little bit salty. Works as both staple and side dish
# 很多来吃饭的人会选择 多加辣子或者少加辣子
Most people who come and eat may choose "more spicy" or "less spicy"
# 你经常能听到一些大人说
And you always hear people say
# 少加点辣子 给娃吃
Less spicy pepper for my kid
# 这边是刚磨出来的米
Here is fresh rice milk
# 米成浆之后就会上锅
After grinding, it's steamed in the steamer
# 我们看一看 刚出来的米皮是什么样子
Let’s see how fresh mipi looks like
# 师傅的动作特别麻利
The movements are so skillful
# 摇晃一下 固定形状
Shake it and fix its shape
# 等待上锅
Wait for steaming
# 一两分钟之后就可以出锅
Ready to serve after one or two minutes
# 啊 我（镜头）已经模糊了
Ah the len is blurry
# 师傅说 米皮一天要蒸的比现在的还要高
Shifu said that they steam more mipi than what we see here
# 能够卖10几摞
More than ten piles of mipi
# 每个米皮出锅都这么掷地有声
Every piece of mipi comes out loud
# 刚才阿姨说 咱们做米皮已经做了第三代了
Aunt said they are the third generation to make mipi
# 第三代 到我这代第三代了
Three generations. I'm the third generation
# 你怎么会选择 继续做米皮呢
Why did you choose to keep the mipi business going
# 当兵回来 出去干了一段时间 不行嘛
After retiring from the army, I tried working elsewhere but didn't go well
# 就是老人说那个
As the elderly say
# 家有万贯 不如一个烂店
Your own bad business is better than good money
# 就把这个手艺继续传承下去
So we must keep the inheritance of the skills
# 咱们是从早上8点到晚上8点半吧 差不多营业时间
We open from about 8 am to 8 pm everyday
# 一天都在营业吗
Whole day?
# 一天都营业
yeah
# 米皮也是不断地蒸 不断地出 不断地切出来
We keep steaming mipi, cutting and serving it
# 早上蒸一点
Steam some mipi in the morning
# 到下午再蒸一点
And then some in the afternoon
# 我看米皮的佐料就是很简单
As I see the condiments of mipi are simple
# 辣椒 盐 简单拌一拌就可以了
Spicy pepper, salt, and mixing it up
# 就可以了
That's it
# 但是越简单的东西 越不好做
But it's even harder to make it simple
# 这个是
You know
# 还有一个就是 会吃凉皮的好多老人
And many old people who eat mipi
# 年龄大的 冬天来 下雪那时候早来
Will come early in the morning, in winter when it snows
# 一早上来吃 8点钟
Around 8am
# 冬天吃凉皮好吃 因为我冬天老吃凉皮
Mipi tastes better in winter, as i always eat it in winter
# 冬天它凉皮凉透了 吃起来有味道
Mipi is fully cooled down in winter, so it tastes more flavorful
# 夏天吃凉皮 皮子也不筋道
If you eat it in summer, it's not al dente
# 冬天凉皮凉一下 筋道
In winter, we cool it a bit, it's al dente
# 小哥刚才说 自己的米皮火不了 因为看了很多人发米皮
Bro said his mipi is not gonna be popular, because he has seen a lot of mipi videos
# 点赞量都不是很高
Not great number of likes
# 除了关心自己的米皮外 他还比较关心我
He does not just care about his mipi, but also me as well
# 说 你可以拍一下喷泉 大唐不夜城 会有助于涨粉
He said I can film that fountain and the Grand Tang Dynasty Ever-Bright City (大唐不夜城), it helps me get subscribers
# 并邀请我们 要走的时候
And he invited us when we left
# 可以再来这边吃一份干捞的米皮 味道会更好
That we can come and eat a ganlao mipi next time, it tastes better
# 时间合适的话 我们一定会再来的
We are gonna come again if we can
# 关 注
# 雪 鱼 探 店
Please subscribe